That's the cookie.
Hello world. Today we invite you to meet
a charming cookie shop and cafe owner,
Chinatsu, or as many of her friends call
her, Chini. She runs a cafe called Black
Sheep in downtown Okayama, which
specializes in big Western-style
cookies, often with a twist, [music]
like these OG Sound cookies that Chini
concocted for Father's Day. Our Scotch
flavored. That's right, whiskey infused
cookies for those who like that smoky
flavor. And of course she sells classics
like chocolate chip and red velvet, too.
Her shop's exterior is loud and
colorful, just like she is. And because
[music] Chini speaks English, she's able
to connect with many inbound tourists
who are looking for a satisfying treat
to refuel them for their next travel
spot.
In this video, we hope to show you not
just a great cafe that you're bound to
enjoy on your next visit to Okayama, but
of an inspiring individual who can take
it on the chin and stand [music] right
back up. Through her unique trials and
tribulations, you could even say that
she hasn't lived a very cookie-cutter
life.
All right, all right. Without further
ado, I'll pass the mic over to Bobby,
our part-time producer in West Japan.
[music]
Thanks, Greg. So, I've known Chini for
years now, but for you viewers, I
thought it might be fun to introduce her
with some rapid-fire get-to-know-you
questions. Okay, number one. Yeah. All
right. How do you take your coffee? Uh
milk. Hamburgers or pizza?
>> Hamburger. Okay. City or country? City.
Okay. What are some songs on your
playlist? Too many.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay, all right.
What's the movie you want to watch on a
date? Last Holiday. So, what's something
that annoys you? Smelly. Smelly? Yeah,
smelly people. And then what's your
favorite holiday? Christmas. Christmas.
But you usually work on holidays.
>> Yeah, so I don't feel like a Christmas
holiday. We have a Christmas party, so
you can go. Oh, yeah, yeah. I would love
to. Yeah.
All right. So, do you believe in ghosts?
Yes. Have you ever seen a ghost? No.
Okay, that's [laughter] fine.
All right. Even though I believe So, now
that you're acquainted, let's take a
look at how Chini starts her days at the
cafe. She usually arrives at 8:00 a.m.
to shape the cookie dough that was
prepared and rested from the day before.
And like many of us in the kitchen,
she's got a morning routine to put her
in the ideal cooking groove.
Music makes me really happy, especially
in the morning.
Mhm. Do you want to smell it?
>> [music]
>> I do like the smell. This is my favorite
job.
Making coffee for me.
>> [laughter]
>> Ah,
saiko.
Before I opened this shop,
like you know, I make coffee for my
parents and my
uh siblings. You know, when I make
coffee for them, they feel
"Wow, good smell. I'm so happy." So,
like you know, oh, I can make a people
happy
with coffee.
I used to live in New Zealand, so the
people are eating cookie with coffee.
The coffee and the cookie are always,
you know, together. And then especially
cookie time, so my daughter, she loves
Cookie Time cookie.
So, I can make her happy.
Um she always has crazy ideas, random
ideas, um
ever since I was little. Like
moving to New Zealand for instance, um
it was out of nowhere, and she would
actually make it happen.
And everyone was surprised, but I grew
up with
those choices and those actions. So,
when she told me that she was going to
open
a cafe
in the middle of Okayama, and she was
going to make it the best, um
I didn't doubt her for a second. I knew
she was going to make it happen, but I
think a lot of people around her doubted
that she was going to make it.
Her friends, mostly family, because they
know her medical condition is very
severe,
and she was hospitalized for about a
year.
So, when she was telling everyone she
was going to open that cafe,
so nobody believed her.
Because my
house
Yeah.
My kidney problems.
I was almost die.
So, I decided to if I die, I want to die
in Japan.
When I was 35, I came back to Japan to
see my parents.
I just I didn't feel well.
So, I just decided to
go to hospital, and then then they said
like it's
quite
serious problem.
You know, I had to go to hospital many
times.
And then my my daughter, she cried a
lot.
So, she couldn't support me by herself,
because I didn't have family.
So, it was really serious.
And then decided, oh, maybe I should go
back to Japan.
And I have parents and a family here, so
I got
I could get
support from them.
And then I stayed in the hospital a year
after I came back to Japan.
How was How was that experience?
That was terrible.
Yeah.
That was really terrible.
I I gained 20 kg.
And then I
then I couldn't move.
I felt like a different person.
Even like my face.
Yeah.
I was really deboo.
>> [laughter]
>> Super deboo that time.
Even like you know, I have problem
health problem now.
I go to hospital, I had to stay in the
hospital
often.
I stayed in the hospital
last month, too.
But
you know, this is my life.
My parents are really happy with me.
They said like I I should try.
Because they also they have own
business.
Especially my my mom, she's really
strong.
She said that I should do it.
Don't be afraid. I just wanted to try.
You never know.
Dialysis.
Yeah.
This one arm always
>> One, yeah, I could I I'm not allowed to
move
this hand. Like always this.
So, I can use this hand.
You know, checking your email and then
your line, you know, all the time, you
know,
my hand this hand is always busy.
>> [laughter]
>> Just retiring, right?
Yeah, but I get used to it.
This is also I just accept it.
Yeah.
First year, second year, I just I
couldn't accept it. I just like you
know, why me?
You know, I couldn't accept it and then
just, you know, I just wanted to die.
I just I didn't want this life anymore.
The but, you know,
the one day I talked to someone, and
they said like even I'm lucky, I can
I get dialysis.
If I change my mind, there's some people
cannot get dialysis, and then they just
waiting for die.
But I'm so lucky. I can get dialysis,
and I can have normal life. I can work,
I can go out,
I can go to restaurant, you know, cafe,
you know,
sometimes like I go to different
country, you know,
but they cannot.
I'm so lucky. I appreciate my life.
Like sounds I'm really good person.
>> [laughter]
>> Right?
>> I'm not.
Do you think you're a selfish person?
Yeah, I think so.
I'm really selfish and you know,
I'm really easygoing.
You can You can ask her or
you can ask Cody.
>> [laughter]
[laughter]
>> Okay.
>> And open stay.
>> [laughter]
[laughter]
>> She's quite young.
Like my son. Same age.
So
I just kind of,
you know, try.
But she's so cute.
>> [laughter]
>> But she's so unique.
So maybe me too. So I can hire
a unique or quirky people.
I don't want like a normal like, you
know,
quiet people.
>> [laughter]
>> It's really sad.
Honestly, I want her to stay, but it's
not good for her. She has to try.
So
I have to say
congratulations.
She should try.
>> [laughter]
[laughter]
>> So far we focused only on the cafe
environment, but let's venture out a
little to one of Chini's favorite
eateries, because despite her busy work
schedule and frequent hospital visits,
Chini makes sure to spend time with
friends and enjoy herself like any other
person.
>> [music]
>> So Chini doesn't just sell her cookies
at Black Sheep Cafe. She also goes to
events in Okayama and in neighboring
prefectures to spread the word. I tagged
along on one such event held in Kyoto
called Whisky Messe. There I met her son
Shua and his employer, who recommended
Chinny to come and sell her cookies to
hundreds of hungry whiskey connoisseurs.
It was a great opportunity not only to
see Chinny outside of her cafe, but to
also see her and Shua's interactions.
And while we were at it, I got a chance
to ask Shua about his time in New
Zealand and connect his experience with
that of his sister's. Uh I was just
before turning 11.
And
Actually, I was very uncomfortable. Um
you know,
not really liking to move out of my
comfort zone. So, yeah. It wasn't
very comfortable time. I did have I
think I did have a very
not very, but pretty hard time.
And
everything changed when I actually
started speaking English,
getting used to the atmosphere.
Um yes, from there I really started
enjoying the you know, life in New
Zealand.
So, my final aim was to actually uh work
in Japan.
And to do that, I knew that it would be
better if I
uh graduated university in Japan.
And if I was to graduate university,
then I should graduate high school in
Japan.
It's not like I I was sick of New
Zealand or something. I I did enjoy
the life, yes, in New Zealand yes, well.
When we first moved moved to New
Zealand,
I think
um
Chinny had multiple jobs or she attended
uh
schools like ELT.
And eventually, she started going to
cooking schools as well. And she had a
lot of jobs
to pay for both of our my brother and I
tuition and her tuition as well. So,
at home, I think she wasn't around a
lot. I was also going through my like
teenage years when I wanted to like be
left alone or not be bothered. So, we I
think it was a perfect timing if that's
like
maybe wrong way to say, but
um we both were
had a lot of own time.
Right now, I think she has a lot of
confidence.
But I think that comes from experience
and what she's overcome in the past. So,
the warmth and the kindness that she
gives to other people and customers who
come to their
her shop is based from her
experience.
Key words to describe my mother would be
crazy
in the good way, best way.
Um outgoing,
very open and warm, welcoming to
anybody.
And very strong, tough
minded.
But I think she's very very unique.
Well, um she doesn't know the feeling of
shameful
cuz you know, like she's really
outgoing. She is very powerful. But
yeah, she's also very caring at the same
time. Not like a person
um that just
goes her own way and leaves others out.
So, I I had a perfect life.
I had the two kids, boy and a girl, and
I built the big house.
And then I had a husband.
And I had everything.
So, financially fine. And I have
parents, siblings, everyone healthy.
But the same time, I feel really scared.
Of what?
I wanted to work at cafe or restaurant.
But I
I didn't have chance.
When I moved to New Zealand, I didn't
speak English at all. Cuz you didn't
have international friends.
>> No.
But I was really curious. Mhm. So, I
needed to think, you know, I have to see
with my eyes and I had to like try
everything.
I was so excited. Like, you know, I
saved money and then I
Actually, I didn't tell anyone.
So, like it's really secret. I was
learning a little bit English,
but not not good.
>> [laughter]
>> So, I was trying to get information and
then I found a really
good agent. Made it like a date when I
moved to New Zealand. So, I just told
everyone. Uh like, you know, actually,
I'm going to New Zealand and they said,
"What?"
>> [laughter]
>> I was a little bit stupid. I didn't
think about it, you know.
If I go there, what's going to happen?
But we met the agent at the airport and
he she picked us. She explained just a
few things and then she said, "Goodbye.
See you tomorrow."
I got a support like a month
Yeah. from her.
Uh
>> Yeah. So, I have to find apartment. I
have to get uh
uh license, car license, license in New
Zealand.
So,
she helped me. So, I we have to open a
bank.
So, I didn't know how. So, she helped me
because I paid.
But after a month,
she just like
bye.
So,
oh [gasps] my god, [sighs] how can I do
it?
I couldn't sleep
at all.
And I met some Japanese women. So, I
just told them like I just want to get
the job at the cafe.
So, everybody said, "Oh, do you speak
English well?" And I said, "Uh actually,
no." And they said, "Oh, sorry. You
can't."
But I just I didn't want to give up.
So, I was telling everyone. So, I want
to get a job at cafe. And then one day,
friend's friends
told me
there's uh
the cafe looking for
the someone.
But not
with contract. Oh, yeah, yeah.
>> So, it's kind of under table.
>> Sure. Yeah. So, I worked really hard. It
was really really hard.
And then I worked 3 months there.
And after that, the owner came back to
New Zealand. She was away. So, I met the
her first and then she just really
appreciate me
because um the
the cafe was really busy. So, I helped
them and then
she said like I can have contract with
them.
I worked with them 2 years and then
I was thinking like I needed some more
step up. And I was thinking to go to
school, cooking school.
And I needed more skills.
And I worked with them a little bit more
longer and then I just moved to
a French restaurant.
Yeah. But when I was working at that
French restaurant,
that is really scared, so scared.
It's quite big restaurant, but the owner
said, "Can you do it?" And I said, "Uh
maybe." He said like, "Maybe?" And I
said, "Yes, I can." "Yes, you can. You
can do it." He just pushed me a lot.
So, I had to do it. Yeah, he's really
good guy. He has so good experience. He
he cooks really well, amazing. He makes
amazing food.
That time I was going to school. I was
learning
the cooking and then studying
from in the morning and after that, I go
to work.
That time I got at three jobs, cleaning,
cleaner and then
I worked with my friend and I worked at
the restaurant.
And then then
I had a boyfriend
and then
sometime I would I spent time with him
like all night and then I go to work.
And then, I go to school.
I didn't have break time
at all.
And then, I also I had to raise my kid.
So,
my body was aching.
But, I just tried to ignore.
If you could go back,
you know, like would you
work less? Of course.
>> Yeah. Of course.
>> yeah, yeah, yeah. And I would tell her,
like
"No worries. Yeah. You can
You can be all right. Don't worry."
But, I just
I don't know why, like you know, I tried
to
be more, like you know, higher and the
higher. Yeah, I was really worried. And
then, you know, always like a
"I can be more. I can be more."
A teacher? Yeah. Yeah, she was told to
make
Yes, I have to take care of myself. I
have to love
me, you know.
I have to take care of my feelings,
love, and my body, too. Yeah.
I always thinking I
have Even like I have my shop.
So, I just I
have to work more and the more.
That's how you feel? Yeah, feel.
And then,
if I get more,
uh for example, if I get the more money,
so I can spend the money for my stuff,
or [snorts] like with my kids, or my
parents, or with my friends.
And I can employ more, you know, people
who
they want to work with me.
But, even there, like you know,
there's some people wanted to work with
me.
But, I said like a uh
maybe I have enough.
That time, I feel really
sorry for them.
If I have a lot of money, I can
employ them, right?
That's the things like it that time I
feel like I really I feel really sorry.
Yeah, even though it's not your fault or
it's not your responsibility.
But, I don't know I If people feels
happy, I feels happy. But, she said that
it's not good. I I The first, I have to
be happy. Then, I can make people hap-
make happy.
That's why I
never regret I left Japan. But, I just
regret I worked too hard.
I didn't care my health.
That's the reason. This is my regret.
I want to enjoy my life a little bit
more with my daughter.
And son. Hm? And son. And son. Yeah, and
son.
Well, folks, that about wraps up our
video on Chini and her cookie cafe,
Black Sheep. I can't say this with 100%
certainty, but Chini is expecting some
big projects in 2026. So, you may not
have to come to Okayama to try Black
Sheep cookies. Wink wink.
>> [music]
>> But, in my opinion, the best Black Sheep
experience will always be with Chini
herself at her shop in downtown Okayama.
Thanks for watching, everyone. Peace.
What are cookie cafes like where you're
from?